en captions for:
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8LxhFSRdIZY
Hey there, time again to build something.
It's cold outside, so I'll just stay in here...
...and do a ready-to-build kit.
It's a "Door/Window Entry Alarm",
as it says.
But I'd rather prefer
what's written on the other side:
A "Guest Welcome Machine"
So, it's a device which,
when someone enters the room...
- or whatever else triggers it -
...makes a sound.
Now, to be totally transparent:
ICStation gave me this.
Links in the description below,
as usual.
So you can get it from them yourself.
If you do, make sure to check the description.
There's a code in there
which will get you 15% off of your purchase.
Anyways, this is not about advertisement.
We're here to see
what the thing actually does
...and how it works.
So let's see
what's inside this lovely cardboard box.
First thing is the manual.
Not really latin letters, unfortunately...
But there's a diagram.
(it's also on the website)
And a list of the components
on the back.
Plus a picture of where everything goes.
At least roughly.
Ok, what else have we got?
A bag of components.
A white case.
Two parts, back and front.
Obviously the speaker will go here
and the sensor at the top.
Also included: 3 LR44.
You know, button cell batteries.
These are the ones with 0% mercury.
You can get them at the local store,
but it's nice to have them included.
So you need not go look for them.
Let's see what's in the bag of components.
Most important is,
of course, the board itself.
For that's where we're going to solder onto.
So it should be of at least some quality.
Now that's pretty standard.
Green solder mask
Looks quite decently manufactured.
No obvious faults to be seen,
so that's ok.
On the other side we've got
component designators printed on.
That's telling which part goes where,
together with the values.
So that should make things pretty easy.
What then catches the eye
is this slot at the top.
Something's supposed to
go in there, apparently.
And of course there is a part
that looks like it'd fit in there.
This is a chip-on-board ("COB").
That means:
underneath the black blob is a microchip.
And these traces connect to it.
That should be what's generating the sound.
We're going to solder it in like this
and thus connect it to the rest.
Then we've got the speaker,
that we've already seen.
It attracts anything metallic
because it has a magnet.
We also need a sensor, of course.
Here we've got something
that looks quite it.
It's a so-called LDR.
or "light dependent resistor".
As the name says,
it's just a resistor.
But it is dependent on light.
So, contrary to the normal ones,
like this one here...
...the LDR doesn't have
a FIXED resistance
...but rather a RANGE
of resistances.
Ie: the amount of light shining on it
...determines the resistance.
We can test this, of course.
Let's just grab the multimeter
and have a look.
So, let's connect the leads.
(doesn't matter which way around)
Looking at the display,
we see some measuring going on.
(takes a little while)
...and we're getting 2.8 - 2.9 kilo Ohms.
However, when I put it in a shadow
with my hand...
...we see it going up.
7 kilo Ohms, 9 kilo Ohms,
10 kilo Ohms, 11 kilo Ohms.
When I take away my hand,
and light's shining on it again...
...it's going down accordingly.
This way, we can tell from the resistance...
if there's currently light or a shadow.
The remaining components are wires,
battery leads,
resistors and transistors.
We'll just sort them a little...
...so we have them handy in a moment.
And now for the manual:
Well, most things can actually be
seen from the circuit diagram.
But I still did some translation.
These two terminals below the slot...
...should connect to the speaker.
Then this one pad at the top...
...that's battery minus.
This here is battery plus.
Finally, we've got the LDR:
It also goes to "Batt+", and
(the other lead) over there.
That's all of our components.
On the other side
we've got this text.
I translated it, too.
(links, again, are in
the description below)
Basically, the text describes
how the whole thing works.
That means: what's coupled to what,
...and how the signal
makes its way to the output.
We'll look at that in a simulation,
which should make things
easier to understand.
Ok, I've put up the
circuit diagram here.
Let's see what we've got.
First thing is the part on the right.
We've got an IC, the T8735,
plus the speaker.
So everything that's
got to do with sound...
...well, we don't solder that ourselves.
It's all already there on the
small part with the black blob.
Now, at the top left
we've got 4.5 Volts.
That's the voltage from the battery.
So there is this positive rail,
going over to the IC.
Likewise, there's the ground rail at the bottom,
which also connects directly to the IC.
So, the only interesting pin of the IC...
...is pin 2, where we have to apply our signal.
Like: "Hello, plz sound now"
Let's see where the signal's coming from.
The other thing on the left is C1.
That's a capacitor, with "104".
"104" stands for a 10 followed by 4 zeros.
So that's 100 nano Farads
(100 000 pico Farads).
100 nF
(easier to remember this way)
C1 should be just for
stabilizing the supply voltage.
These button cells aren't made
for putting out large currents.
And I guess, particularly
when the speaker goes off...
...that might draw a
lot of current for a moment.
C1 then makes up for that.
Next up is our old friend, RG.
Actually I don't know why it's "RG" here.
It's just the LDR.
The light dependent resistor.
Now, who can name this:
one resistor on top and another
below, going to minus?
Well, that is nothing but
a voltage divider.
So we've got two voltages top and bottom,
and another voltage at the center.
Let's assume there's light on the LDR.
That was about 12 kOhm.
[No, it was 3 kOhm with light]
The lower one is 82 kOhm,
That gives about 4V between the two.
[Actually: 4.4V with light on the LDR]
The only thing connected there is C3,
which is a 1 micro Farad capacitor.
What does it do?
Well, it charges up
- and that's it.
For now let's say
it's a dead-end there.
Nothing else happening here.
We'll come back to that.
But let's first look at the rest.
For understanding the rest,
we've got to go kind of backwards.
Two transistors here.
The upper is a PNP,
the lower an NPN.
So: the upper get's "plus" from here...
...and connects through
if it gets "minus" at the base (middle pin).
While the lower connects through
to minus is the base is positive.
Now, what if the upper one
is currently conducting?
We would have a high potential
connected to pin 2 of the IC.
Which can be viewed as a kind of signal.
As said: assuming "minus"
at the base of Q1.
Let's check if there really is a "minus".
Well, there's 4.5V over R1.
So Q1 is switched off at first.
But Q1's base is also connected to C2.
C2 is a "103" capacitor,
that means a 10 followed by 3 zeros.
10 followed by 3 zeros
means 10 nF.
Let's put down 10 nF,
so we can remember.
Well, actually what C2 does
is only a bit of filtering.
That is, C2 is not really relevant
(for now).
But: there's also Q2
(connected to Q1's base).
Q2 gets "plus" fed in
(to its collector).
But it CAN connect to "minus"...
...if it's got "plus" on its base.
Has it "plus" on the base?
Yes, it has.
Namely over R2,
the "20 meg-Ohms"...
...there's "plus" at Q2's base...
...and the drawing is messed up!
Because: Q2 is now conducting.
That means everything below
R1 is now at "minus", not "plus".
At "ground potential"
(or something near 0V)
Which, on the other hand,
means that Q1 is switched ON.
So Q1 let's current flow through.
Ok, good...
But...
Not only do we need current,
we also need to react to RG, right?
Now comes into play...
...a characteristic of capacitors,
namely of C3.
Usually, when put between "plus" and "minus",
it stores some voltage [charge]. Like C1.
And that's correct for C1.
But:
it's different for AC
[alternating current]
Any CHANGE in voltage
- is propagated through!
Voltage changes from where?
From RG!
Our LDR, the light-dependent resistor.
Remember: its resistance VARIES
from 3 kOhm to 12 kOhm.
So those 4V are not fixed.
Might be 4.4V as well
(when LDR is @ 3 kOhm, not 12 kOhm)
That's a difference of 0.4V
And these 0.4V of difference
do show up on the other side of C3.
On the other side, however,
this difference appears inverted...
Errm...
So, since R2 is a very large resistor...
...only a small current is coming through,
which is "used up" for compensating
for the voltage swing at C3.
So Q2 gets no current into
its base and switches off.
Therefore there's plus on Q1's base,
and IT switches off.
That in turn "disconnects"
pin 2 of the IC.